Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
Thomas Gray Manuscripts: An Integrated Finding Aid
[ca. 1725]-1771
grayt.ead.0001#did0001
manuscripts, letters
Thomas Gray (1716-1771) et al.
Thomas Gray Archive Oxford, UK
An integrated finding aid to all known Thomas Gray manuscripts, autograph or transcript (by contemporaries and early editors), currently listing Gray's poetry manuscripts only. Catalogued in EAD 2002 by Alexander Huber and first published by The Thomas Gray Archive in 2006. This finding aid is work-in-progress: when completed, it will contain all known Thomas Gray manuscripts, including his prose works, personal papers, and marginalia. The finding aid will also be continually enhanced as original materials are made available to the Archive and digital surrogates are being created.
Administrative Information
Restrictions
Please consult with the repository holding the original manuscript using the contact information provided with each of the manuscript records.
About the Originals
In this finding aid, the Archive provides collection-level description and location information for Thomas Gray MSS. More information about the original manuscripts themselves is available from the holding repositories, contact information of which can be found with each manuscript entry.
Scope and Content
Thomas Gray Manuscripts: An Integrated Finding Aid lists all of Gray's identified autograph poetry manuscripts as well as transcripts in the hands of his contemporaries and early editors of his works. Each of the $c03num manuscript entries provides basic bibliographic and archival information, including a physical description wherever possible. Where available, the records contain links to digital surrogates of both the original manuscripts and the first printed edition of the work. This guide builds on a number of print and online information sources, among which the ones listed in the bibliography have been particularly helpful and are herewith duly acknowledged. This finding aid is work-in-progress: when completed, it will contain all known Thomas Gray manuscripts, including his prose works, personal papers, and marginalia.
Bibliography
Crum, Margaret (ed.): First-Line Index of English Poetry 1500-1800 in Manuscripts of the Bodleian Library Oxford, 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969
Jones, William Powell: Thomas Gray, Scholar. The true tragedy of an eighteenth-century gentleman. With two youthful notebooks now published for the first time from the original manuscripts in the Morgan library, New York City. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP, 1937
Jones, William Powell: "Thomas Gray's Library". Modern Philology 35(3) (Feb. 1938), 257-278
Poetic Commonplace Books and Manuscripts of Thomas Gray, 1716-1771, from Pembroke College, Cambridge. Listing and guide to the microfilm collection. Published by the University of Cambridge, Pembroke College. Reading: Adam Matthew Publications, 1991 [2nd ed. 1999]
Munby, A. N. L.: "Thomas Gray". A. N. L. Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues of Libraries of Eminent Persons, Volume 2: Poets and Men of Letters. London: Mansell; Sotheby Parke-Bernet Publications, 1971, 1-82
National Register of Archives: Gray, Thomas (1716-1771), poet. The National Archives. 04 May 2010. <http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/nra/searches/subjectView.asp?ID=P11979>
Nelson, Carolyn W. (ed.): Union First Line Index of Manuscript Poetry 13th-19th Century (bulk 1500-1800). Dec. 2012. Folger Shakespeare Library. 15 February 2013. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/>
Smith, Margaret M.: "Thomas Gray: 1716-1771". Margaret M. Smith (ed.), Index of English Literary Manuscripts, Volume III: 1700-1800, part 2: John Gay - Ambrose Philips. London and New York: Mansell, 1989, 71-116
Sutton, David C. (ed.): Location Register of English Literary Manuscripts and Letters. Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries, Volume I: A-J. London: The British Library, 1995, 413-415
Arrangement
Following the example in contemporary indices and location registers of MSS, Thomas Gray Manuscripts is arranged alphabetically by uniform titles of works, as found in the Primary Texts section of Thomas Gray Archive. The individual manuscript witnesses are listed chronologically. However, autograph MSS are always listed before transcripts. Please note that works for which no known MS copy exists, have not been included.
Biographical Information
Thomas Gray was born in London in 1716 and died in Cambridge in 1771. He was a poet, letter-writer, scholar, critic, and avid reader and commentator, whose published output during his lifetime remained slim, yet who left behind a large and varied manuscript output. See the Archive's biographical sketch or chronology of Thomas Gray for more information.
Controlled Access Terms
Personal Names (LCNAF)
Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771
Subjects (LCSH)
Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771--Manuscripts; Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771--Diaries; Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771--Correspondence; Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771--Notebooks, sketchbooks, etc.; Poets, English--18th century
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - Ad C: Favonium Aristium, Barbaras aedes aditure mecum; 1775; poems.lt01
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 138-140 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 306-308 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Cambridge when Gray was about to join Richard West (Favonius) at the Inner Temple, where they intended to study law together. First published, untitled but referred to in a footnote as a Sapphic Ode, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section I, letter no. XIV. Mason is the only source for this letter, dated June 1738, in which Gray originally sent the poem to West. MS translation into English by Thomas Wharton.
    - Ad C: Favonium Aristium, June 1738; mss.0001; poems.lt01; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Microfilm copy available in
      Poetic Commonplace Books and Manuscripts of Thomas Gray, 1716-1771, from Pembroke College, Cambridge (1999), reel one
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 1, 79
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 21
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 136
      Autograph fair copy, annotated "Cambridge. June, 1738 " in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, split over two pages: p. 53 (ll. 1-40) and p. 90 (ll. 41-52).
    - Ode on Mr. West's leaving the University, 1780[?]; mss.0233; poems.lt01; 6 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode on Mr. West's leaving the University (p. 1) (Ode. I. [p. 3]). The poem is part of a section called Latin Pieces, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 24), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - Ad C: Favonium Zephyrinum, Mater rosarum, cui tenerae vigent; 1775; poems.lt02
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 144-145 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 310-312 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Rome in the Spring of 1740 while on the Grand Tour with Horace Walpole. First published, untitled but referred to in a footnote as Ad C. Favonium Zephyrinum, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section II, letter no. XXI. Mason is the only source for this letter, dated May 1740, in which Gray originally sent the poem to West (Favonius). MS translation into English by Thomas Wharton.
    - Ad C: Favonium Zephyrinum, Spring 1740; mss.0003; poems.lt02; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 2, 79
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 22
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 138
      Autograph fair copy, annotated "Wrote at Rome, the latter end of the Spring, 1740. after a journey to Frescati & the Cascades of Tivoli", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 128.
    - Alcaïca, May 1740; mss.0004; poems.lt02; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Poetic Commonplace Books and Manuscripts of Thomas Gray, 1716-1771, from Pembroke College, Cambridge (1999), reel two
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 3, 79
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 33
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Alcaïca, endorsed in an unidentified hand "by T. Gray, from Tivoli".
    - Ode to Mr. West, [between 1776 and 1804]; mss.0002; poems.lt02; 3 transcript and English translation in the hand of John Phillipps 193 mm x 160 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Duke Humfrey's, Bodleian Library, on 02/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 79
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 668, item O754
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=76914>
      Transcript in the hand of John Phillipps (f. 43), followed by an English translation headed Translation (ff. 43v-44r), in a volume of collected verse, copied from manuscripts, printed editions and newspapers, by John Phillipps of the Middle Temple and Exeter College, Oxford, 1776-1804 (Summary Catalogue, 45759).
    - Ode to Caius Favonius Zephyrinus, 1780[?]; mss.0234; poems.lt02; 5 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode to Caius Favonius Zephyrinus (p. 7) (Ode II. [p. 9]). The poem is part of a section called Latin Pieces, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 24), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - Agrippina, a Tragedy, 'Tis well, begone! your errand is performed.; 1775; poems.agtr
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 84-92
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 27-43
    Written at London, after returning from the Grand Tour, during the winter of 1741-42 and abandoned by 23 April 1742. First published in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 125-135. Mason is the only source for the two letters (one not extant and one dated [1?] April 1742 ) in which Gray originally sent the prefatory matter and scene I (ll. 1-182) of the fragmented drama to West. Scene II (ll. 183-194) was probably also finished before 23 April 1742, although it has been suggested that it might have been composed as late as the winter of 1746-47.
    - [untitled], [17??]; mss.0198; poems.agtr; [1?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie, partial [dramatis personae and ll. 1-20] 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 169, 96
      Sutton (ed.), Location Register (1995), 414
      Ellner, June, "Re: MS 30/44, James Beattie papers". E-mail to the editor, 20 December 2006
      Transcript of the dramatis personae and ll. 1-20, here untitled, in the hand of James Beattie, together with Beattie's comments.
  - [Alcaic Fragment], O lachrymarum Fons, tenero sacros; 1775; poems.lt03
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 140-141 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 308 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Cambridge when Gray was about to join Richard West at the Inner Temple, where they intended to study law together. First published, untitled, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section I, letter no. XIV. Mason is the only source for this letter, dated June 1738, in which Gray originally sent the poem to West.
    - [untitled], [1738?]; mss.0007; poems.lt03; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 5, 79
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 137
      Autograph fair copy, untitled but identified in the index at the end as Tears, (Latin Alcaïc) fragment on them, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 90.
  - [Alcaic Ode], O Tu, severi relligio loci; 1775; poems.lt04
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 151-152 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 317-318 (with English prose translation)
    Gray wrote this poem in the album of the monastery of the Grande Chartreuse on this second visit on 21 August 1741, during his journey from Turin to Lyon, when he was returning alone from the Grand Tour. First published, as Ode, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 117-118. MS translation into English by Thomas Wharton.
    - In the Book at the Grande Chartreuse among the Mountains of Dauphiné, August 1741; mss.0008; poems.lt04; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 6, 79
      Autograph fair copy, headed In the Book at the Grande Chartreuse among the Mountains of Dauphiné, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 129.
    - Gray's Ode on visiting The Grand Chartreuse – written in The Album of the Fathers, [1807?]; mss.0005; poems.lt04; 1 transcript in the hand of Joseph Hunter 167 mm x 103 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Northup, Bibliography (1917), item 1997
      Transcript, entitled Gray's Ode on visiting The Grand Chartreuse – written in The Album of the Fathers, in the hand of Joseph Hunter, in a volume prefaced Silva Poetica ( 1807 ).
    - Ode to the Deity of the Grand Chartreuse, [between 1776 and 1804]; mss.0006; poems.lt04; 3 transcript and English translation in the hand of John Phillipps 193 mm x 160 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Duke Humfrey's, Bodleian Library, on 02/10/2006.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 674, item O877
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=77055>
      Transcript in the hand of John Phillipps (f. 42), followed by an English translation headed Translation (ff. 42v-43r), in a volume of collected verse, copied from manuscripts, printed editions and newspapers, by John Phillipps of the Middle Temple and Exeter College, Oxford, 1776-1804 (Summary Catalogue, 45759).
    - Ode composed at the Grande Chartreuse, 1780[?]; mss.0235; poems.lt04; 4 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode composed at the Grande Chartreuse (p. 13) (Ode III. [p. 15]). The poem is part of a section called Latin Pieces, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 24), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - [The Alliance of Education and Government. A Fragment], As sickly plants betray a niggard earth; 1775; poems.aleg
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 93-97
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 85-100
    Written in 1748-49 and probably abandoned by March 1749. Gray sent ll. 1-57 of the fragment in a letter, dated 19 August 1748, to Thomas Wharton. First published, entitled Essay I, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 193-200.
    - Essay 1st, [1749?]; mss.0012; poems.aleg; 2 autograph; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 9, 79
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 27
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 144
      Autograph, headed Essay 1st, with numbered lines (5, 10, etc.), followed by a quotation in Greek from Theocritus in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. II, 619-620.
    - [untitled], 19 August [1748]; mss.0010; poems.aleg; 2 autograph fair copy, partial [ll. 1-57] and revised 238 mm x 180 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 7, 79
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 146, vol. i, 308-312 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, revised, of ll. 1-57, here untitled, followed by MS 0011, in a letter to Thomas Wharton, 19 August [1748]. Beneath the poem is written "I desire your Judgement upon so far, before I proceed any farther", and "Pray shew it to no one (as it is a Fragment) except it be St:r who has seen most of it already, I think".
    - [untitled], [before 1794]; mss.0011; poems.aleg; 3 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton, partial [ll. 58-107] 230 mm x 185 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 8, 79
      Transcript of ll. 58-107, untitled, in the hand of Thomas Wharton, following a letter by Gray, containing ll. 1-57, to Wharton, 19 August [1748] (see MS 0010).
    - An Essay on Education and Government, [17??]; mss.0009; poems.aleg; [?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Transcript in the hand of James Beattie, entitled An Essay on Education and Government and annotated in his hand "This beginning of an ethical play is finished in the Author's highest manner. He began it in the year 1748, as appears from a letter to one on his friends inclosing a part of it. In that letter, he entitles it, An Essay on Education and Government, or rather, on the necessary alliance of them to produce the external happiness of mankind. He relinquished the prosecution of this work on the publication of M. de Montesquieu's Esprit des Loix: a book which he highly admired; and which he said had forestalled the principal things he meant to advance upon the subject. And yet we see, from what he has here left, that he differed from the Baron in one material point, viz, the influence of soil or climate on national manners."
  - The Bard. A Pindaric Ode, 'Ruin seize thee, ruthless king!; 1757; poems.bapo
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 18-24
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 177-200
    Begun late in 1754 and initially abandoned by August 1755, then taken up again, completed and revised, between May and August 1757. Gray sent the earlier parts of the poem in letters to Thomas Wharton, dated 6 August 1755 (ll. 1-56), and to Richard Stonhewer, dated 21 August 1755 (ll. 63-100), the latter part (ll. 111-144) to William Mason, dated [24 or 31] May 1757. First published, as Ode II. in Odes by Mr. Gray ( 1757 ), 12-21.
    - Bard, 21 August 1755; mss.0014; poems.bapo; 1 autograph, partial [2 lines] 204 mm x 160 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 10, 80
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 205, vol. i, 433-434 (subscription required)
      Autograph proposal of a revision of ll. 17-18, here beginning, "With fury pale, & pale with woe," in a letter to Thomas Wharton, 21 August 1755.
    - [untitled], 27 August 1756; mss.0015; poems.bapo; 1 autograph, partial [ll. 23-56]; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 11, 80
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 222, vol. ii, 474-478 (subscription required)
      Autograph, of ll. 23-56, here untitled but referred to as "the British Ode", in a letter to Edward Bedingfield, 27 August 1756.
    - [untitled], [beginning of June 1757]; mss.0016; poems.bapo; 4 autograph draft, partial [ll. 57-144] 226 mm x 187 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 12, 80
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 205A, vol. i, 434-437 (subscription required)
      Starr, Gray's Craftsmanship (1946), particularly pp. 424-429
      Autograph draft, of ll. 57-144, here untitled, following a letter to Thomas Wharton, 21 August 1755, but according to
      Correspondence of Thomas Gray (1971), vol. i, 434
      very probably written at the beginning of June 1757.
    - [untitled], [24 or 31] May 1757; mss.0017; poems.bapo; [1?] autograph fair copy, partial [ll. 111-144]; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 13, 80
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 238, vol. ii, 501-503 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, of ll. 111-144, untitled but headed "Antist: 3a." and beginning "Haughty Knights, & Barons bold", in a letter to William Mason, [24 or 31] May 1757.
    - [untitled], [1757?]; mss.0018; poems.bapo; 1 autograph, partial [argument]; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 14, 80
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 29
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 208
      Autograph argument of the ode, here untitled, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. II, 932v. First printed in Mason's Poems ( 1775 ), 91.
    - [untitled], [1757?]; mss.0019; poems.bapo; [9?] autograph, revised and partial [notes only]; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 15, 80
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 788(?), 20, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53(?), 45, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 241, 73
      W[right]., Catalogue (1851), [lot 53?,] 13
      Autograph notes to the poem, revised, in Gray's copy of Odes by Mr. Gray ( 1757 ). The notes were first published in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0020; poems.bapo; 2 autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 16, 80
      Autograph notes to the poem, untitled but numbered 6. and identified on f. 3r as 6. The Bard, a Pindaric Ode, beginning "Prefix the original advertisement, The following Ode is founded &c:", in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0021; poems.bapo; [2?] autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 17, 80
      Heist, Michael, "RE: Modern (Bound) Manuscripts, vol.52, Robert H. Taylor Collection". E-mail to the editor, 11 January 2007
      Autograph notes to the poem, headed "Prefix the origl. advertisement, The following Ode is founded, &c:", in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
      The letter in which these instructions were originally sent is now at Historic Collections, King's College, University of Aberdeen, Aberdeen, UK.
    - Gazetta Litteraire de l'Europe. 1764. Tom: 3. p: 259, mss.0022; poems.bapo; 3 autograph transcript; ETON
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 18, 80
      Sutton (ed.), Location Register (1995), 413
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 606, 10
      Autograph transcript of a translation into French prose, headed Gazetta Litteraire de l'Europe. 1764. Tom: 3. p: 259. The translation is unlikely to be Gray's.
    - The Bard, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0013; poems.bapo; 1 transcript of variant lines in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 142, 128, 130] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 80
      Transcript of variant versions of ll. 142, 128, and 130, in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 182r.
    - Bard, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0203; poems.bapo; 1 transcript of variant lines in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 142, 128, 130] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of variant versions of ll. 142, 128, and 130 (crossed out), in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 33r.